There's this quote by activist and punk rock musician Jello Biafra that I love.
تعجبني مقولةٌ قالها الناشط وموسيقي البانك روك جلو بيفر.
He says, "Don't hate the media. Be the media."
يقول فيها "لا تكره الإعلام بل كن أنت الإعلام."
I'm an artist.
أنا فنان.
I like working with media and technology because A, I'm familiar with them
أعشق العمل مع التكنولوجيا ووسائل الإعلام أولاً: لأنني مطلعٌ عليها،
and I like the power they hold.
و معجبٌ بمدى قوتها.
And B, I hate them and I'm terrified of the power they hold.
وثانياً لأنني أكره وأخشى قوتها.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I remember watching, in 2003, an interview between Fox News host Tony Snow
أذكر مشاهدتي لمقابلة بين مذيع فوكس نيوز، توني سنو،
and then-US Defense Secretary, Donald Rumsfeld.
و وزير الدفاع الأمريكي السابق، دونالد رامسفيلد ، في عام ٢٠٠٣.
They were talking about the recent invasion of Iraq,
كانا يتحدثان عن الغزو الأخير للعراق،
and Rumsfeld is asked the question,
و سُئِلَ رامسفيلد :
"Well, we're hear about our body counts,
"حسنا، نحن نسمع عن عدد جثث جنودنا،
but we never hear about theirs, why?"
ولكن لا نسمع عن عدد جثثهم على الإطلاق، لماذا؟"
And Rumsfeld's answer is,
وجواب رامسفيلد هو:
"Well, we don't do body counts on other people."
"حسنا، نحن لا نحصي جثث الآخرين"
Right?
صحيح؟
It's estimated that between 150,000 to one million Iraqis, civilians,
تشير التقديرات إلى أن ما بين ١٥٠٫٠٠٠ إلى مليون من المدنيين العراقيين،
have died as a result of the US-led invasion in 2003.
ماتوا نتيجة للغزو الذي قادته الولايات المتحدة عام ٢٠٠٣.
That number is in stark contrast with the 4,486 US service members who died
هذا العدد يناقض تمامًا ٤,٤٨٦ من افراد الجيش الاميركي الذين لقوا حتفهم
during that same window of time.
خلال تلك الفترة الزمنية نفسها.
I wanted to do more than just bring awareness to this terrifying number.
لم أرد فقط أن أرفع مستوى الوعي بهذا الرقم المخيف،
I wanted to create a monument for the individual civilians
بل أردت إنشاء نصب تذكاري للمدنيين
who died as a result of the invasion.
الذين لقوا حتفهم نتيجة الغزو.
Monuments to war, such as Maya Lin's Vietnam Memorial,
النصب التذكارية للحرب، كنصب مايا لن التذكاري لحرب فيتنام،
are often enormous in scale.
غالبا ما تكون ضخمة الحجم.
Very powerful and very one-sided.
كما أنها قوية و تشكل وجهة نظرٍ واحدة.
I wanted my monument to live in the world, and to circulate.
أردت لنصبي التذكاري أن يعيش وينتشر في العالم.
I remember when I was a boy in school,
أتذكر عندما كنت صبيا في المدرسة،
my teacher assigned us this classic civics assignment
أن معلمي خصص لنا واجباً حول التربية المدنية الكلاسيكية،
where you take a sheet of paper and you write a member of your government.
حيث تستلم ورقة وتكتب فيها عضوًا في حكومتك.
And we were told, if we wrote a really good letter,
وقيل لنا حينها أننا لو كتبنا رسالة جيدة ،
if we really thought about it,
لقد فكرنا في ذلك حقًا ،
we would get back more than just a simple formed letter as a reply.
فسنتلقى أكثر من مجرد رسالة جوابية.
This is my "Notepad."
هذه مفكرتي.
What looks like an everyday, yellow legal tablet of paper
التي تبدو مجرد ورقة صفراء عادية،
is actually a monument to the individual Iraqi civilians
هي في الواقع نصبٌ تذكاري للمدنيين العراقيين،
that died as a result of the US invasion.
الذين ماتوا نتيجة للغزو الأمريكي.
"Notepad" is an act of protest and an act of commemoration
"المفكرة" هي فعل احتجاجي وإحياءٌ لذكرى
disguised as an everyday tablet of paper.
متخفية كورقة من مفكرة عادية.
The lines of the paper, when magnified,
تظهر سطور الورقة حين يتم تكبيرها
are revealed to be micro-printed text
لتبدو نصًا بطباعة ميكروسكوبية،
that contains the details, the names, the dates and locations
بحيث يحتوي على التفاصيل، والأسماء، و المواعيد و المواقع ،
of individual Iraqi civilians that died.
الخاصة بالضحايا المدنيين العراقيين.
So, for the last 5 years, I've been taking pads of this paper, tons of this stuff,
لذلك، لمدة سنوات ٥ الماضية، قمت بأخذ أكوام من الورق وطن من هذا،
and smuggling it into the stationery supplies
وتهريبها إلى لوازم القرطاسية
of the United States and the Coalition governments.
للولايات المتحدة وحكومات التحالف.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I don't have to tell you guys this is not the place to discuss how I did that.
لا يجب عليي أن أخبركم كيف فعلت ذلك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But also, I've been meeting one-on-one with members and former members
وكذلك أجريت مقابلات مع أعضاء حاليين وسابقين
of the so-called Coalition of the Willing, who assisted in the invasion.
لما يسمى ب"تحالف الراغبين"، الذين تعاونوا على الغزو.
And so, whenever I can, I meet with one of them,
ولذا أقابلهم بقدر الإستطاعة ،
and I share the project with them.
وأشاركهم هذا المشروع .
And last summer, I had the chance to meet
و في الصيف الماضي أُتيح لي فرصة مقابلة
with former United States Attorney General and Torture Memo author, Alberto Gonzales.
النائب العام السابق للولايات المتحدة و مؤلف "مذكرة التعذيب"، ألبرتو غونزاليس.
(Video) Matt Kenyon: May I give this to you?
(فيديو) مات كنيون: هل بيمكني أن أعطيك هذا؟
This is a special legal tablet.
هذه لوحة قانونية خاصة.
It's actually part of an ongoing art project.
هي في الحقيقة من ضمن مشرع فني مستمر.
Alberto Gonzalez: This is a special legal pad?
ألبيرتو جونزالز: هذه لوحة قانونية خاصة؟
MK: Yes. You won't believe me,
مات: نعم. لن تصدقني،
but it's in the collection of the Museum of Modern Art; I'm an artist.
ولكنها مجموعة لمتحف الفن الحديث؛ أنا فنان.
MK: And all of the lines of the paper are actually --
مات: وجميع خطوط الورقة هي في الواقع --
AG: Are they going to disappear?
ألبيرتو: هل ستختفي؟
MK: No, they're micro-printed text
لا،النص مطبوعٌ في حجم ميكْرُوسْكُوبِيّ
that contains the names of individual Iraqi civilians
بحيث يحتوي على أسماء المدنيين العراقيين،
who have died since the invasion of Iraq.
الذين لقوا حتفهم منذ غزو العراق.
AG: Yeah. OK.
ألبيرتو: نعم، حسناً.
AG: Thank you. MK: Thank you.
ألبيرتو: شكراً. مات: شكراً
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The way he says "thank you" really creeps me out.
طريقة شكره فعلاً تثير القشعريرة.
OK, so I'd like each of you to look under your chairs.
حسناً، فلينظر كلٌ منكم لأسفل كرسيه.
There's an envelope.
يوجد ظرف.
And please open it.
أرجو منكم فتحه.
The paper you're holding in your hand
الورقة التي بين يديكم
contains the details of Iraqi civilians that died as result of the invasion.
تحتوي على تفاصيل عن المدنيين العراقيين الذين ماتوا نتيجة للغزو.
I'd like you to use this paper and write a member of government.
أرجو أن تستخدموا هذه الورقة كي تكتبوا إلى عضوٍ في الحكومة.
You can help to smuggle this civilian body count
يمكنكم أن تساعدوا في تهريب هذا العدد من الجثث
into government archives.
إلى الأرشيف الحكومي.
Because every letter that's sent in to the government,
كل رسالة تم إرسلها إلى الحكومة،
and this is all across the world, of course --
من جميع أنحاء العالم، بطبيعة الحال--
every letter that is sent in is archived, filed and recorded.
كل رسالةً أرسلت هي مؤرشفة و محفوظة و مسجلة.
Together, we can put this in the mailboxes and under the noses of people in power.
معاً نستطيع وضع هذه في صناديق البريد و تحت نظر أصحاب النفوذ.
Everything that's sent in
كل شيء يُرسل
eventually becomes part of the permanent archive of our government,
يصبح في النهاية جزءً من الأرشيف الدائم لحكومتنا،
our shared historical record.
الذي هو سجلنا التاريخي المشترك.
Thank you.
شكرُا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Tom Rielly: So, tell me Matt,
توم رايلي: إذن، أخبرني يامات،
how did this idea come into your head, of "Notepad"?
كيف خطرت لك فكرة "المفكرة" ؟
Matt Kenyon: I'd just finished a project
مت كنيون: انتهيت للتو من مشروع
that dealt with the US Coalition side of the war
يتناول قضية من جانب التحالف الأمريكي للحرب،
and it was a black armband that was called the "Improvised Empathetic Device"
وهناك شارة سوداء تسمى "الجهاز التعاطفي الإرتجالي"
which accumulated, in real time,
التي جمّعت في وقتٍ حقيقي،
the names, ranks, cause of death and location
معلوماتٍ الأعضاء الذين توفوا في الخارج أثناء الحرب ،
of US service members who had died overseas,
من حيث الأسم، و الرتبة ، و سبب و مكان الوفاة .
and each time the Department of Defense or CENTCOM released their data,
وفي كل مرة تنشر وزارة الدفاع، أو القيادة المركزية الأمريكية معلومات،
it would stab me in the arm.
فإني أشعر بطعنة في ذراعي.
And so, I became aware that there was a spectacle
وهكذا أدركت أن هناك مشهدا
associated with our own people who were dying overseas,
يتعلق بمواطنينا الذين كانوا يموتون خارج البلاد،
but a disproportionate amount of casualties
ولكن القدر المتفاوت من الضحايا
were the civilian casualties.
كان من الضحايا المدنيين.
TR: Thank you so much.
توم: شكراً جزيلاً لك.
MK: Thank you.
مات: شكراً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)